<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-01T16:36:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Penmanship dialects of the Roman alphabet</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/penmanship-dialects" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Penmanship dialects of the Roman alphabet" /><published>2020-12-29T14:29:54-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-29T14:29:54-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/penmanship-dialects</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/penmanship-dialects">&lt;p&gt;It’s very common to see people of Chinese, Taiwanese or Japanese origin writing the cross bar of the ‘t’ character first when they write in English. English natives, in fact the majority of users of the Cyrillic alphabet, will write this stroke last. Most will wait until the word is written before returning to add the cross bar on this character because there’s a tendency not to take the pen off the paper between letters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/penmanship-dialects/spencerian-workbook.jpg&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this is the way native English speakers are taught at school; using cursive or ‘joined up’ handwriting whereas characters in Asian languages such as Japanese tend to have a lot of short strokes, with the pen regularly taken off the paper when forming characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;gallery&quot; id=&quot;chimney-swifts&quot;&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/penmanship-dialects/chimney-swifts/chimney-swifts_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/penmanship-dialects/chimney-swifts/chimney-swifts_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/penmanship-dialects/chimney-swifts/chimney-swifts_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look closely, you’ll see the penmanship of a native Japanese speaker tends to be strikingly neat and precise when writing the English alphabet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/penmanship-dialects/penmans-art-journal.jpg&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might notice that the top and bottom of the ‘S’ character are very parallel and exact. The cross bar of the ‘t’ character might appear right in the middle of the vertical line, whilst a native writer would be more likely to put it towards the top of the &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/penmanship-dialects/#-ascender&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;--ascender&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;-ascender&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;ascender&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
. Overall the letters appear very balanced, perhaps reflecting the precision required when writing Japanese kanji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, precision is often the giveaway when you’re writing in a language that isn’t your first one. When you’re writing in a language that’s less familiar than your mother tongue, you’ll often aim for a degree of precision that identifies you as a foreigner. Native speakers can afford to write more sloppily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/penmanship-dialects/covfefe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Covfefe in calligraphy.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Because, let's keep this going...and calligraphy practice.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also be that we unconsciously shape our handwriting to a form we’re more familiar with. Some Chinese and Taiwanese people often write English characters using sharper angles, whereas a native English speaker might write more rounded characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Older people might also have a preference for using block capitals, rather than the tricky cursive style that’s more alien to non-native speakers. For Arabic and Farsi speakers, there’s a tendency to write letters slanted slightly to the left, so the handwriting appears somewhat italic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Germany had its own unique writing system, the Sütterlin script, taught in German schools for much of the 20th century. Although it’s less common now, it’s easy to identify an older generation of Germans, who learned this until as late as the 1970’s, by their written script. It’s often fairly illegible to non-Germans (as well as some younger Germans). Although Sütterlin is no longer taught, the German handwriting style is still fairly distinctive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calligraphy has been used for more than just written communication since it’s onset. &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/penmanship-dialects/#-calligraphic-art&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;--calligraphic-art&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;-calligraphic-art&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;Calligraphic art&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
 is a beautiful form of drawing, especially used to render animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curious differences in how we write numbers
You’ll find many differences in the way the numbers are written across cultures. The number 7 can be written very differently by people from different backgrounds, although it does tend to be recognizable to all however it is written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally the 7 was written with a serif stroke at the upper left, and the horizontal stroke is written with a curve or wave form. You’ll often still see this serif when it’s written by someone from China or Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some cultures add a crossbar, which helps distinguish it from the number one. That’s especially common in cultures where the one is written with an upstroke on the top, such as in France. You’ll see the cross bar used when the writer comes from France or other parts of Europe, and it’s also seen in Australian penmanship. Sometimes writers from Taiwan will even use two horizontal crossbars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Germany had its own unique writing system, the Sütterlin script, taught in German schools for much of the 20th century. Although it’s less common now, it’s easy to identify an older generation of Germans by their written script. Although Sütterlin is no longer taught, the German handwriting style is still fairly distinctive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number 9 is also written differently by people from different cultures. Some parts of Europe add a curved hook underneath the character, making it somewhat resemble the letter “g” with its &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/penmanship-dialects/#-descender&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;--descender&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;-descender&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;descender&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
. Elsewhere it tends to be written with a straight vertical line and no hook at the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some parts of Asia the number 9 is written with other striking differences: in South Korea the looped part of the number is uniquely located either above the vertical stroke, or even to the right of it (making it resemble the letter ‘p’). To most other parts of the world this makes the number appear as if written backwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proliferation of typing on a computer, as opposed to hand writing on paper, perhaps suggests that the differences between our written characters might begin to die out.
It’s hard to see how cultures can continue to write numbers differently when the forces of globalization are bringing us increasingly close together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as Germany has now moved away from its unique style of handwriting, it’s likely that handwriting around the world could become increasingly homogenous over time. But these changes take time: new generations of writers are always taught by older generations that retain their cultural identities in their penmanship. The cultural accents evident in our handwriting may continue to persist for some time yet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lia Prins</name></author><category term="penmanship" /><category term="language" /><category term="all" /><category term="design" /><summary type="html">Believe it or not, the way in which we form our letters can often help identify our culture of origin and even our mother tongue. Although we may achieve a high level of fluency in another language, it’s surprisingly hard to abandon the style of penmanship that we were first taught. Whether it’s the length of our pen strokes or where we place a cross bar, our handwriting retains our cultural identity through all the languages we learn to write in. The order in which we make strokes when writing letters is just one example of our handwriting ‘accent’.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How are Martian mountains measured?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/martian-mountains" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How are Martian mountains measured?" /><published>2020-09-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/martian-mountains</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/martian-mountains">&lt;p&gt;A baseless claim?
It’s true that no agreed upon or precise definition of a mountain base exists. In fact, there’s not even a universally accepted definition for mountain itself. Nonetheless, I’m certain that one of my geology-related homework readings from the previous millenium claimed that Mauna Kea — the volcano that forms most of the Island of Hawai’i — is taller than Mount Everest if you compare them from base to summit, since Mauna Kea’s base extends below sea level to the ocean floor. Assuming this decades-old elementary school assignment was justified in its claim, what threshold or criteria was used to constitute Mauna Kea’s and Everest’s respective bases?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of Mauna Kea, its base turns out to be fairly apparent. As a shield volcano born of the Hawai’in hotspot, its lava pillowed out to form an upward slope relative to the sea floor. Furthermore, the combined weight of Mauna Kea and its fellow volcanoes depress the oceanic crust below them by an estimated 8 kilometers (4.9 miles),1 which results in an underwater moat ringing the chain of islands, known as the Hawai’in Trough. The bowing of the sea floor causes the surface outside the weight-bearing region to rise up even higher, forming an arch where the crust buckles upwards. This all makes it simple — though still somewhat subjective — to tell where Mauna Kea begins, so to speak. From the bottom of the Hawai’in trough to its top, Mauna Kea comes in at about 9.7 kilometers (6.0 miles) tall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/crust-depression.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A cross-section of Mauna Kea, showing the depth to which it depresses the crust below (8,000 meters) and around it (5,000 meters), as well as a resulting arch raised 200 meters above the adjacent seafloor.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    The Island of Hawai’i, which includes Mauna Kea as well as other volcanoes, is so massive that it puts a literal dent in the crust below it. This in turn results in a seafloor trough ringing the region, as well as an arch further out where the crust is raised about 200 meters (656 feet) above the rest of the seabed.&lt;p class=&quot;figcaptionspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;(Note that the horizontal scale is squished so that I could fit everything in!)
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mount Everest and other Himalayan peaks are fold mountains, resulting from the collision of the Australian-Indian tectonic plate into the Eurasion plate. The materials these mountains are made from more or less match those of the surrounding land, the way a wrinkle in a rug is made of the rug itself, although the crumpled nature of the Himalayan range does reveal older (and therefore normally buried) layers of the crust. This — and the fact that the “rug” from which it arises is itself not necessarily on a horizontal or flat “floor” — make Everest’s base a much more arbitrary call. Proposed base elevations for Everest range from 4.2 kilometers (2.6 miles) on its south to 5.2 kilometers (3.2 miles) on its north in the Tibetan Plateau, which — when averaged and subtracted from the peak’s 8,848-meter (29,029-foot) elevation — result in a summit-to-average-base height of 4,148 meters (13,579 feet).!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;gallery&quot; id=&quot;mauna-kea-vs-everest&quot;&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/mauna-kea-vs-everest/mauna-kea-vs-everest_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1st alt!&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          1st caption!
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/mauna-kea-vs-everest/mauna-kea-vs-everest_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2nd alt!!&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/mauna-kea-vs-everest/mauna-kea-vs-everest_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;3rd alt!&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          3rd caption :D
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving home base
Despite its uncomfortably abstract squishiness, this base-to-summit measurement method seems to work in some cases, at least conceptually. Given that many of the extraplanetary promontories that us Earthlings have come to be aware of are volcanic in origin (and as we’ve seen in the case of Mauna Kea and Everest, a volcanically created peak generally lends itself to a much more apparent base than mountains and ranges caused by tectonic forces), perhaps this approach can be applied to extraterrestrial mountains, too?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;gallery&quot; id=&quot;helium-balloons&quot;&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/helium-balloons/helium-balloons_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1st balloon alt!&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/helium-balloons/helium-balloons_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2nd balloon alt!!&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          2nd balloon caption!!
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/helium-balloons/helium-balloons_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;3rd balloon alt!&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          3rd balloon caption :D
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mars is the perfect planet to start with, as it’s propagated a number of truly massive shield volcanoes, many plenty heavy enough to crush the crust beneath and around them into indentations — just like the Hawai’in islands do. Several are also sharply defined by sheer escarpments — 8 kilometers (5 miles) high in some places — that aid in creating distinctive thresholds with which to delineate the volcanoes’ boundaries. These cliffs are likely the result of erosion at the outer edges of past lava flows.4 However, the bases of these pedestal-like scarps surrounding the peaks’ perimeters are at different heights relative to each other, so it’s still tricky to determine where to set the starting point of each mountain. Nonetheless, Olympus Mons is easily Mars’ tallest mountain, coming in at nearly 22 kilometers (13.7 miles) from the foot of its northwestern cliffs to its peak.5 Despite its height, it has an average slope of just 5 degrees, spreading over a footprint of 300,000 square kilometers (120,000 square miles),6 roughly the area of New Mexico.7 It’s so large that, according to astrophysicist Neil deGrasse Tyson, “you could be on its slopes and you would not know [it] … the base is so huge before you get to its summit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/olympus-mons-new-mexico.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A photo of Olympus Mons evidencing its enormity relative to the size of the state of New Mexico.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Olympus Mons’ footprint falls only about 4,400 square kilometers (1,700 square miles) short of New Mexico’s.&lt;p class=&quot;figcaptionspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;Image credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/spaceimages/details.php?id=PIA02982&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mountain that came from outer space
Volcanoes aren’t the only way that interplanetary peaks come to be, though. With an average width of just under 530 kilometers (or 330 miles),9 4 Vesta is the second-largest known asteroid within our Solar System. It hosts a crater called Rheasilvia that takes up most of its southern hemisphere, the bottom of which lies about 13 kilometers (8.1 miles) below the surrounding surface.10 Rheasilvia likely formed from a collision so colossal that the impacting body made its way through several layers of crust and possibly even into 4 Vesta’s mantle,11 as evidenced by spectral signatures of olivine — the primary mineral composing Earth’s own mantle — captured by the Hubble Telescope.12 Beneath layers of post-pummel debris, the remnant of the impacting body itself forms the foundation of a soaring summit at the center of the crater. This peak is essentially deadlocked with Olympus Mons for tallest known mountain in the Solar System13 both behemoths’ undulating surroundings — and therefore the large margins of error surrounding their extremely approximated baselines — make it impossible to objectively discern which deserves the honor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/4-vesta.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A composite image of Vesta 4, showing Rheasilvia's bump on its south pole.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Rheasilvia forms a very visible bulge near 4 Vesta’s southern pole.&lt;p class=&quot;figcaptionspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;Image credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eso.org/public/images/potw1826a/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;European Southern Observatory&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, a mountain’s base-to-summit height is significantly subjective, even if there happen to be cooperative geological features at play like troughs, craters, or cliffs. While this measurement method may result in an interesting — if conceptual — trait of the peak in isolation, it neglects to capture the global context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earth as an ellipsoid
Unlike the base-as-a-baseline approach, sea level excels at accurately plotting a peak’s height relative to the rest of the world. This metric has been a reliable reference point throughout the history of height measurement, providing an ostensibly consistent surface from which to determine elevations. According to the National Geodetic Survey — a branch of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration responsible for establishing latitudes, longitudes, elevations, and shorelines in the US — sea level is defined locally, via various tide surveying stations. Each is constantly collecting sea level data for its own region. Mean Sea Level (MSL) is then defined for each locality by averaging those measurements over the course of 19 years, “the period over which the pull of the sun and the moon on the earth completes a full cycle.”14&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory, sea level serves as the stalwart starting point from which to map the elevations of disparate global locations. But in practice, it’s not quite so simple. It helps here to first have a bit of context about Earth’s overall shape, to better understand the disparity between theoretical and practical sea level. Our planet is not a perfect sphere: all distances from its center of mass to its surface are not equal, and not just because of the bumps caused by the very mountains we’re seeking to measure. Earth’s diameter from pole to pole is about 42.8 kilometers (26.6 miles) shorter than its equatorial diameter — a difference of about ⅓ of a percentage point — which makes our planet an ellipsoid or an oblate spheroid, geometrically speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/ellipsoid.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A quarter-slice of a perfect circle overlaid on a quarter-slice of Earth's ellipsoidal form, to show the slight sliver of difference.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Earth bulges seemingly imperceptibly at its equator; the difference between its ellipsoidal shape and a perfect sphere is shown in dark blue.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earth is just shy of spherical because it spins. The further a point is from its axis of rotation (like a location along the equator), the faster that point must travel through space, compared to points that are closer to the axis (like those nearer the poles). This difference in relative speed results in a phenomenon called centrifugal force. Over time, this bit of extra force has flung Earth’s innards outwards, which has led to a slightly deformed spheroid shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After averaging away tidal pull, currents, and weather-induced waves, one would expect the oceans to settle into a flat, global plane — the very embodiment of the ellipsoid model. However, even after accounting for 19-years-worth of tides, this appears not to be the behavior of our seas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To quote spatial analyst Witold Fraczek: “The reference ellipsoid was intended to closely approximate the MSL; it was surprising when the figures differed greatly.” This wasn’t realized until relatively recently, when the TOPEX/POSEIDON satellite — launched in 1992 expressly to capture surface altitudes16 — revealed that sea level, even after time-averaging, differed from the ellipsoid by as much as 100 meters (330 feet) in some spots.17 In other words, our oceans appear to have hills and valleys of their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sea level doesn’t seem level
What keeps sea level from spreading out evenly over Earth’s ellipsoidally averaged surface? It actually turns out to be gravity that is not evenly dispersed across the earth, and the seas in turn reflect this. Earth’s crust varies invisibly in its density: in some places comprised of hollow caverns, porous layers, or water-logged aquifers, all of which are much less dense than solid rock — but even rock differs in density from type to type significantly. Moreover, to quote the National Geodetic Survey, “Mountains have greater density and, therefore, cause greater gravitational acceleration than valleys that are mostly filled with air. … If it has lower density than its surroundings, it produces less gravity.”18 And it is gravity that supplies the very characterization of a level surface: like the tool of the same name, level is defined as perpendicular to the gravitational field.19 Therefore, though the oceans may appear to undulate unevenly, given that they do so in response to Earth’s gravity, they are in fact level by definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/ellipsoidal-sea-level.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A map simulation of southeast Asia, wherein the sea level has lowered near New Guinea but risen to cover Bangladesh.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    A world with no gravitational anomalies — in which the mass of the Earth is distributed completely homogeneously — would result in new shorelines, shown in green. Sea level would lower between New Guinea and Australia, but rise to cover Bangladesh.&lt;p class=&quot;figcaptionspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;Image credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.esri.com/news/arcuser/0703/geoid2of3.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Environmental Systems Research Institute&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the time-averaged, temperature-normalized surface of the sea, the strength of gravity is exactly equal, and this lumpy, oceanic expanse equates to the actual reference used by surveyors to define elevations, known as the geoid.20 It extends across the continents too, though — oscillating through raised land masses and over empty valleys, forming a lumpy layer defined by a strength of gravity exactly equaling that at sea level. Scientists use an abundance of different technologies to measure micro-variations in gravity across the continents (a fascinating can of worms that I may pry open in a future post all its own). But another — far more analog — way to find the geoid at any land-based location would be to dig a channel from the ocean inland to that exact point, then wait to see where sea level settled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/canal-geoid.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A sketch of North America with a canal dug straight across, and a cross-section of that canal showing the water level rising slightly at the Rockies and other mountainous regions.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    To determine the geoid’s height at any inland point, we could theoretically excavate a canal to the sea: the height of the water there will match that of the geoid, by definition. This extension of sea level will be pulled higher where it passes through taller and denser land masses, due to the increased gravity they create.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that the mass of a mountain makes its own gravity, how much taller would it be if it weren’t weighed down by this same self-induced gravity? That is, how would a mountain’s height change if we didn’t take into account the relative bulging of the geoid at its exact location?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original geodesists seeking to measure Mount Everest as a part of British India’s Great Trigonometric Survey claimed that there were “grounds for inferring that sea-level under Mount Everest would be raised by 150 feet on account of the attraction of the mighty mass above it.”21 Subtracting this alleged 150 feet would yield Everest’s ellipsoidal height, and is essentially based on the ellipsoid rather than the geoid. Put another way, we’d ignore the gravitational anomalies that the geoid accounts for, in favor of the visually flat surface provided by the reference ellipsoid — that smooth and mathematically perfect geometric form based solely on the discrepancies between Earth’s polar and equatorial diameters, and which disregards variations in density and landmass. The geoid and the ellipsoid intersect at geoid undulations: direct results of the non-homogeneous nature of Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/geoid-vs-ellipsoid.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A sketch overlaying the crust with mountains, values, and varying densities; the ellipsoid's boundary; and the geoid. Where the crust rises to form hills, the geoid also rises relative to the ellipsoid, though not so high as the crust itself. Where the crust is denser, geoid also rises.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    How much taller would a given mountain (or dense patch of crust) be without taking into account the gravity it creates (and therefore the hypothetical “sea level” it attracts)? We could instead measure from the ellipsoid (periwinkle line) — which essentially averages all Earth elevations to a perfectly smooth plane — to get an “ellipsoidal height”, rather than measuring from the geoid (red line), which gives us the commonly used “orthometric height”, often referred to as elevation above sea level.&lt;p class=&quot;figcaptionspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;(Differences between the crust, geoid/mean sea level, and ellipsoid are very exaggerated in this diagram to make their relationships clearer.)
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the geoid is quite lumpy relative to the ellipsoid, it’s not as rugged as Earth’s actual crest- and canyon-riddled crust, because although gravity does vary in strength due to these landforms, their physical effects on gravity are not equal to their physical volumes. A mountain cannot produce the gravity required for a river to flow all the way uphill to its top; however, it might generate enough that water near it would settle at a relatively higher elevation than if that mountain weren’t there. The fact that the geoid takes these sorts of gravitational variations into account make it a far superior model for floodplain mapping and the like compared to the ellipsoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/geoid.gif&quot; alt=&quot;An animation of the Earth's geoid (greatly exaggerated in shape) spinning.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    The geoid’s lumpiness is vastly exaggerated here, but serves to show areas of Earth where the pull of gravity is relatively stronger and weaker due primarily to the location, size, and density of landmasses.&lt;p class=&quot;figcaptionspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;Image credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://oceanservice.noaa.gov/facts/geoid.html&quot;&gt;NOAA&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extraterrestrial elevations
Since scientists have identified a geopotential plane from which to measure height on our planet, it would seem at least theoretically possible that this same concept could be applied to other planetary bodies … and in fact, it has: this extraterrestrial equivalent of the geoid is called an areoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other planets aren’t often enveloped in oceans the way Earth is, though, so how are areoids’ baselines chosen? And if they’re anywhere as arbitrary as the bases of the mountains they aim to quantify, what’s the point?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of Mars’ areoid, its “zero” level had initially been based on atmospheric pressure: the minimum pressure at which water is stable, also known as its triple point.22 Anything lower than this and ice is capable of skipping its liquid phase and sublimating straight into gaseous form (the way dry ice does even at Earth’s normal surface pressure, since carbon dioxide — the molecule it’s composed of — has a much lower triple point of its own). The thought was that a hypothetical water-based Martian ocean — with a hypothetical sea level from which to measure elevations — could only exist at a pressure below water’s triple point. Otherwise, by definition, there would be no liquid to form imaginary oceans in the first place — just solid ice and water vapor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/triple-point-areoid.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A sketch wherein Olympus Mons perches upon a line representing the Martian areoid's base, and extending 21 kilometers above it. Everest's peak is drawn a scaled distance of 30 kilometers below the line.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    The original method used to establish the Martian areoid was based on atmospheric pressure. It put the baseline at the planet’s surface, notwithstanding higher landmasses like Olympus Mons, which rises about 21 kilometers (13 miles) above this pressure-defined baseline. If we were to use that same atmospheric threshold to measure elevations on Earth, even Everest — our highest point — would earn itself a negative measurement: about -30 kilometers (-18.6 miles). Given that Mars is sea level-less (and our own sea level is rather randomly based on the amount of water that happened to accumulate on Earth), the pressure-baseline approach affords a way to compare interplanetary elevations. However, those very comparisons come at the cost of seeming nonsensical.&lt;p class=&quot;figcaptionspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;(Again, horizontal dimensions are nowhere near to scale; you can just assume they won’t be unless I say otherwise!)
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The atmospheric pressure at sea level on Earth is just 0.6% of water’s triple point,22 however, so if we were to base our own geoid on that metric rather than sea level, it’d mean our geoid’s baseline would be high in the sky, no matter your Earth-bound location. Everest’s elevation would recalibrate to (very) approximately -30 kilometers (-18.6 miles) — that’s right, a negative elevation23 — compared to its current elevation of 8,848 meters (29,029 feet). It’s clearly much easier for our surface-dwelling minds to make use of a sea-level-based reference point. All of this means that a triple-point-calculated Martian areoid and the elevations it results in aren’t particularly comparable to those on Earth, thereby rendering them far less relatable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sea level, sans seas
Fortunately for those of us in dire need of more fathomable (and accurate) Martian elevations, in 2001 the Mars Orbiter Laser Altimeter provided scientists with enough gravity information to reformulate Mars’ areoid.24 They now knew where the pull of gravity was relatively stronger and weaker, and could map the concentric gravity gradients that surround the planet like the layers of an onion — each ring its own geopotential surface exhibiting an exactly equal pull of gravity. Earth is circumscribed by its own geopotential surfaces, of which our geoid is one. For convenience and for comprehension, the baseline of the geoid was chosen to match that of the gravity potential at sea level, but it need not have been. It could have been set as a physically higher geopotential surface, but therefore with lower gravity potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/onion-rings.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Earth and Mars ringed by concentric wobbly circles, indicating geopotential lines of decreasing strength as they move outward.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    The geopotential surfaces mapping equal strengths of gravity extend below and above any planet’s surface. Since these planes are the basis from which we measure elevations, it makes sense to choose one as a baseline that matches the surface’s circumference closely.&lt;p class=&quot;figcaptionspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;(I exaggerated the gravity anomalies (that is, the squiggliness of the “onion rings”) here to visualize the fact that planes of equal gravity are bumpy in direct response to the planet’s uneven density.)
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But on a Mars unmarred by el mar, how does one choose which onion ring to call “zero”? Scientists settled on the geopotential surface for which the mean radius matches that of Mars’ equator.25 This doesn’t necessarily mean that every point along the Martian equator lies at zero inches in elevation, though: like on earth, a surface defined by equal gravity thereby responds to gravity directly, not to physical features (although it may be indirectly affected by land formations in so far as they in turn affect gravity to a degree), and will therefore vary in its distance from the crust, rising above ground in some places and falling below it in others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like Earth’s geoid, Mars’ areoid also exhibits areas in which gravitational disruptions reflect topographical ones. Olympus Mons and the Tharsis region near it — home to some very voluminous volcanoes — produce the largest gravity anomalies in the entire Solar System.26 Olympus Mons came in at 22 kilometers (13.7 miles) high when measuring from the base of its bounding cliffs, but its summit is only about 21 kilometers (13 miles) above the Martian areoid.27 This is the inverse of what we saw with Everest, wherein its elevation is much greater than its base-to-peak height. Olympus Mons’ transposed elevation-to-height ratio actually serves to further emphasize its sheer magnitude: it produces its own gravity (with a lot of help from its neighboring Tharsis Montes and the magma-spawned plateau upon which they perch), thereby raising the areoid’s “onion ring” in its region and leading to elevation measures that are lower due to the areoid’s swell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/olympus-mons-vs-everest.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Olympus Mons and Everest side by side, with demarcations of their areoid and geoid respectively, as well as their baselines. Olympus Mons' baseline is below its areoid, while the reverse is shown of Everest.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Most Earthly elevations are greater than the base-to-summit measurements of their mountains. On Mars, though, Olympus Mons is so massive that it pulls the planet’s areoid higher in its region, to the point that the difference between its peak and the areoid is about 1,000 meters (3,280 feet) less than the height of the mountain itself (from its natural base).
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems sensible to develop areoids for planets and moons exhibiting elevated land formations, but scientists have even developed them for the gas giants, too. Like Mars’ initial areoid, those of Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, and Neptune are based on pressure. Their baselines fall at the radial distance from their planet’s center of gravity wherein the atmospheric pressure equals 1 bar,28 which is just under the pressure at sea level on Earth. This threshold actually ends up falling right at the cloud levels that visibly define the “surface” for each of the gas giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lower gravity and lack of tectonics lend a leg up
Although areoids provide a helpful way to compare elevations across planets, they fail to account for the fact that bodies with lower mass exhibit lower gravity: namely, the pull that Martian mountains contend with is just 38% the strength of Earth’s, making it much easier for them to sprout skyward. To literally level the playing field, I normalized for Earth’s gravity (in an overly simplistic, possibly precarious way29), and found that beneath its strain, Olympus Mons only makes it to the 8.4 kilometer (5.2 mile) mark when measuring from its base to its summit (compared to 22 kilometers (13.7 miles) under its own planet’s gravity), falling just short of Mauna Kea’s 9.2 kilometers (5.7 miles).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/earth-gravity-on-olympus-mons.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A scale drawing of Olympus Mons from the side, overlaid on a drawing of how much flatter it would be if it grew up under Earth's gravity.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Assuming there’s a more or less linear relationship between a volcano’s height and the gravity exerted upon it, an earth-bound Olympus Mons might have only ever grown to about 8.4 kilometers from base-to-summit.&lt;p class=&quot;figcaptionspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;(Finally a sketch that is more or less to scale! Although I did have to do some experiments and estimations (silly putty was involved) to get an approximation of Olympus Mons’ would-be diameter on Earth, assuming its volume stayed the same…)
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mars’ relatively low gravity isn’t the only pinnacle-producing trick the planet has up its proverbial sleeve, though: lack of tectonic motion plays a prominent role in the heights that its mountains have managed to reach. Most of the Martian shield volcanoes are significantly more massive than any on Earth, in part because their crustal locations stay statically positioned above the hotspots from which the peaks originate.30 Meanwhile, the land above Earth’s hotspots are never in the same spot for long (geologically speaking), due to our planet’s plate movements. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;-1&quot; class=&quot;notenumberinline s-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-notes-id=&quot;1&quot; data-notes=&quot;&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
 This explains why the Hawai’in hotspot led to a chain-like formation of several sea mounts, rather than a single skyscraping summit in the middle of the Pacific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/martian-mountains/hawaii-hotspot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Raised-relief map of the Pacific basin, showing seamounts and islands trailing the Hawai’i hotspot in a long line terminating near the Kamchatka Peninsula in Russia.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    The Hawai’in hotspot has stayed stuck in place, while the Pacific plate moved in a northwesterly direction, evidenced by the trail of islands and seamounts scattered from Hawai’i’s Big Island to the hotspot's first creations, now near the Kamchatka Peninsula in Russia.&lt;p class=&quot;figcaptionspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;Image credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/mgg/image/2minrelief.html&quot;&gt;NOAA&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made me wonder about the Hawai’in hotspot’s lava-output potential relative to that of Olympus Mons’: if the Pacific plate had stayed still, how vast a volcano could it have produced? To get a rough idea, I simply used the collective volume of the Hawai’in chain of islands and seamounts — nearly 750,000 cubic kilometers (180,000 cubic miles) — as a proxy for Mauna Kea’s would-be size on a hypothetical, tectonic-less Earth … I say “simply” on my part, because someone else had already written a paper about the hotspot’s total output &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;-2&quot; class=&quot;notenumberinline s-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-notes-id=&quot;2&quot; data-notes=&quot;&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
 And equally fortunate for me and my free time, NASA had already done the legwork to determine Olympus Mons’ volume at 3,862,000 cubic kilometers (just under 2,400,000 cubic miles). &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/martian-mountains/#-centrifugal-force&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;--centrifugal-force&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;-centrifugal-force&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;Centrifugal force&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
 From there, it was just a matter of division to discover that over five Hawai’in-hotspot-outputs-worth of lava would fit inside of Olympus Mons!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/martian-mountains/#-el-mar&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;--el-mar&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;-el-mar&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;El mar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, as far as the mountains of the world — that is, the Solar System, if not the universe — are concerned, this is all just semantics. And I think that’s more or less where I’ve landed as well. The behemoths of the land (and sea, and space) are wild things, unbridled by our attempts to bestow metrics and accolades upon them. A mountain’s human-assigned height will always carry with it a whiff of the arbitrary, but from now on when I read an elevation on a map, I’ll understand all that went into it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lia Prins</name></author><category term="science" /><category term="geology" /><category term="Mars" /><category term="mountains" /><category term="volcanoes" /><summary type="html">On maps, a mountain’s height is always shown solely as its peak’s elevation above sea level. This seems like a bit of a cop-out to me&amp;#58; is the mountain itself really that tall? Or is it just standing on the shoulders of a very tall plateau, so to speak? Then again, determining the base from which to measure any mountain seems like quite the slippery slope once you get down to it, so I do understand and sympathize with the sea level approach adopted by us Earthlings. But what about pinnacle-peppered planets and oceanless asteroids — (how) do we measure their mountains?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Casting light on the moon’s dark side</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-moons-dark-side" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Casting light on the moon’s dark side" /><published>2018-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-moons-dark-side</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-moons-dark-side">&lt;p&gt;But why does the moon keep the same side toward &lt;em&gt;Earth!&lt;/em&gt; all the time? To do this, it revolves exactly one time on its axis for every one time it circles Earth, which seems like a remarkable coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/the-moons-dark-side/telescope-view.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;I am alt text&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    I am a &lt;a href=&quot;http://liaprins.com/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;; I am &lt;em&gt;italicized&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;p class=&quot;figcaptionspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;More text oh yeah oh yeah ohhhh yeahhhhhhhh
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, think of how the Moon causes major tides on the Earth due to the Moon pulling at the Earth via its gravitational field. The Earth has this same effect on the Moon and, being 81.28 times more massive, the effect is much more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as the mass of the Moon is attempting to go one way (in a straight line), the Earth is simultaneously pulling it another way (towards the Earth). Further, the effect of the Earth’s gravitational field is stronger on the side of the Moon closest to the Earth than on the far side (and the same with the Moon’s gravitational field’s effect on the different parts of the surface of the Earth). To peak around to the &quot;dark&quot; side of the moon, NASA used the Hubble telescope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This combination essentially stretches the Earth and Moon, creating tidal bulges on both celestial bodies. This occurs on both sides of each, with the bulge on the sides closest together from gravity and on the sides farthest away from &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/the-moons-dark-side/#-inertia&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;--inertia&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;-inertia&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;inertia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
. In the latter case, the matter is less affected by the gravitational force with inertia dominating in this instance. To put it another way, the matter is trying to move in a straight line away from the Earth and the gravitational forces here aren’t as strongly able to overcome this, which creates the bulge on that side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why does the moon keep the same side toward Earth all the time? In order to do so, it has to revolve exactly one time on its axis for every one time it circles Earth, which seems like a remarkable coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So back before the Moon was tidally locked with the Earth, the bulge on the side of the Moon nearest to Earth ended up slightly leading thanks to &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/the-moons-dark-side/#-friction&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;--friction&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;-friction&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;frcition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
 and the fact that the Moon rotated faster than its orbital period around the Earth. So with this slightly leading bulge being offset from the line of gravitational pull between the Moon and Earth, this created a torque, which overtime resulted in the Moon’s rotation slowing until it became tidally locked with the Earth; thus, only one side faces the Earth. (Note: the bulge on the far side of the Moon had the opposite effect, but the bulge closest to the Earth dominated the interaction.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll note, though, that I said we actually get to see about 59% of the surface of the Moon from Earth, not 50%. The discrepancy comes from the fact that the Moon’s orbit around the Earth isn’t perfectly circular, more of an ellipse. As the Moon’s distance from the Earth increases and decreases, its angular speed changes, while its rotational speed stays the same. The result is that we get to see an extra 9% of its surface than we would if it had a perfectly circular orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other side of this, as you may have guessed, is that the Moon has the same effect on the Earth and is gradually slowing the Earth’s rotation in the exact same way the Moon became tidally locked with the Earth. Further, as the Moon slows the Earth’s rotation, a small portion of the Earth’s rotational momentum gets transferred to the Moon’s orbital momentum, with the result being that the average radius of the Moon’s orbit increases at about 3.8 centimeters per year with the current continental positions and barring major geological events. (Contrary to what you’ll often read, the Moon isn’t getting all the energy here, most of it is being converted to heat via friction, with only an estimated 3% of the energy in the interaction being “stolen” by the Moon.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the distance between the Moon and the Earth changes gradually and is more or less in step with the rotational period change. It should be noted, though, that it’s not a constant change as things like major earthquakes, glacial changes, continental drift, and other such geological events play a role here, which is why leap seconds aren’t always added at regular intervals, but sometimes when needed. Other times extra leap seconds, called &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/the-moons-dark-side/#-haversine&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;--haversine&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;-haversine&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;haversines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
, are also added as needed. But the overall effect is that over time, the Moon is getting farther and farther away from the Earth every year, while the Earth’s rotation is slowing down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory, at some point tens of billions of years from now (with the exact timeframe being extremely difficult to nail down due to so many unknowable factors) the same side of the Earth will always face the Moon, with the Earth only rotating once per lunar cycle, which at that point most estimates indicate should be about 47 current Earth days long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In theory”… but this will likely never happen. Why? In about 1 to 2 billion years or so, the Sun’s brightness will have increased sufficiently to vaporize all water on the surface of the Earth, getting rid of the ocean tides altogether, which is a huge factor in this interaction. However, there still would be some bulging of the Earth’s crust to continue the process to a much lesser extent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/the-moons-dark-side/solar-system-traffic.jpg&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 5 to 6 billion years, the Sun will be around the peak of its Red Giant phase, and according to the latest models, even with the Sun losing quite a bit of mass during this process, thus making the Earth’s orbit farther out, the Sun should just barely consume the Earth and Moon many billions of years before such a dual tidal lock can occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bottom line, at some point in the next billion years or so, humans will need to either find another home, or figure out how to manually move our current one to a farther out orbit, keeping Earth in the habitable zone of our solar system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lia Prins</name></author><category term="science" /><category term="physics" /><category term="astronomy" /><category term="moon" /><category term="sun" /><summary type="html">Way back in seventh grade science class, I wrote on the back of my spiral-bound notebook &amp;#58; “Is it just a coincidence that the moon both rotates around Earth at a certain speed and spins at a certain rate that ends up so it is always keeping the same face toward us?” It made no sense to me; other planets' moons don't behave this way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The measure of a mountain</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/measure-of-a-mountain" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The measure of a mountain" /><published>2017-04-09T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/measure-of-a-mountain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/measure-of-a-mountain">&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, sea level is not level. The distance from the center of the Earth to the coast­line is different around the world, not only because of winds and weather, but also as a result of the Earth’s midsection bulge, which causes water {and everything else} to spread out at the equator. In addition, Earth is lumpy, with massive topographical features {such as mountains} altering the gravity in surrounding areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the long run, though, snow might actually be more of a bane than a boone for a mountain’s height. Geologists had wondered for a while whether it was just a coincidence that taller peaks tended to cluster closer to the equator. That was until research into erosion rates done by David Egholm of Aarhus University in Denmark revealed that the slow, [tectonic-collision]-fueled growth of most mountains is no match for the mountain-munching forces of glaciers and ice. The snowline of crests at lower latitudes is likely to lie at a much higher elevation compared to the those of their more polar peaks, many of which are coated in a thick blanket of snow from tip to toe year round–and by blanket I mean gritty sandpaper that scours a mountain’s surface away, whole boulders at a time. This means that unless you’re lucky enough to be a Himalayan peak or a pinnacle in one of a handful of rare ranges whose vertical growth outpaces the damage done by glacial erosion, your height is likely to top off at about [1,500 meters] above your snowline, which in turn would seem to favor the equatorial summits, the snowlines of which are [staved off to higher elevations by their more tropical climates].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love this planet. That’s why I have such a cool pen. The magnitude-7.8 earthquake that rocked Nepal in April 2015 may have changed the Himalayas’ heights buy a couple of inches at most. But just how do scientists measure that miniscule level of change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Official measures put Mount Everest at 29,029 feet (8,848 meters) above sea level, but recent satellite data suggest the sky-scraping peak may have shrunk by about 1 inch (2.54 centimeters), because the un­derly­ing tectonic plates have relaxed somewhat. Even the alpine forests’ tree rings were shaken. Regular text above 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Official measures put Mount Everest at 29,029 feet (8,848 meters) above sea level, but recent satellite data suggest the sky-scraping peak may have shrunk by about 1 inch (2.54 centimeters), because the underlying tectonic plates have relaxed somewhat. Even the alpine forests’ tree rings were shaken. Regular text above 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading below 1
Accurately measuring miniscule changes in a mountain that is more than 5 miles up is no easy feat, but surprisingly, measurements rely on geometric formulas and surveying techniques that haven’t changed all that much since the 1800s, said Peter Molnar, a mountainous geologist at the University of Colorado, Boulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading above 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regular text below 2. At heart, measuring a mountain relies on basic ninth-grade math. To calculate the elevation of a mountain, scientists would measure the distance between two points on the ground and then measure the angles between the top of the mountain and each point. Regular text above 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading below 3
“If you have two angles, you know the third, because the sum of the angles is 180 [degrees],” Molnar told Live Science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading above 4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regular text below 4. To carry out these measurements, surveyors must identify a horizontal surface using a level (which, like the kind at a hardware store, relies on a trapped air bubble that, under the influence of gravity, slides closer to or farther away from a central region as it tilts). From there, surveyors eye the summit and measure the angle with the assistance of a glorified, highly accurate protractor — a telescopic device known as a theodolite. With two angles and one side of a triangle, trigonometry reveals the lengths of the other sides, and thereby, the height of the triangle (the mountain). Regular text above 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regular text below 5. Welsh surveyor and geographer Sir George Everest used just this repetitive technique to measure the height of the world’s tallest mountain located in the Himalayas in the 1840s. Of course, one measure could be mistaken, so teams of geographers calculated the dimensions of the mountain from myriad different stations at the base of the mountain, averaging out the heights calculated with many, many triangles. Regular text above 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regular text below 6. Legend has it that when the team took the average of all of those measurements, they found the mountain was exactly 29,000 feet (8,839 m) tall, Molnar said. Regular text above 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading below 7
“They didn’t expect anybody to believe it, so the story is they added 2 feet [0.6 m], just to make it look more believable,” Molnar said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading above 8
Regular text below 8. The official height of Mount Everest is based on a survey conducted in 1955.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading below 9
Regular text below 9. Nowadays, however, basic trigonometry gets a boost from an army of satellites circling the globe. When a satellite pings a receiver tower on Earth, it can calculate that point’s location in a given coordinate system with incredible precision; the calculation relies on two known factors: the radio signal travels at the speed of light; and the satellite is located at a known position relative to the Earth’s center at a given time. Because geographers placed a receiver tower near the top of Everest, they were able to get a more precise measure of its height.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading above 10
Regular text below 10. In addition, the Earth is curved. That means the distance between two points on the ground is actually an underestimate, and the error is proportional to the distance between the two points divided by the radius of the Earth. That means two surveying stations can’t be more than a few miles apart before reasonable amounts of error creep in, Molnar said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even that is an approximation. The Earth isn’t perfectly spherical; it has a bulge at the equator, making the poles 16 miles (26 km) closer to the center of the Earth than a point on the equator. To account for that discrepancy, surveyors need to add another correction term, Molnar said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on tradition, mountains are typically measured not from their bases, but from sea level, which is typically considered the average of the low and high tides in an area. Unfortunately, “sea level is not level,” Molnar said. The distance from the center of the Earth to the coastline is different around the world, not only because of winds and weather, but also as a result of the Earth’s midsection bulge, which causes water (and everything else) to spread out at the equator, Molnar said. In addition, Earth is lumpy, with massive topographical features (such as mountains) altering the gravity in surrounding areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you measured sea level coming from Calcutta to Nepal, or coming from Bombay, you might wind up with a different answer,” Molnar said, referring to the Indian cities that are now called Kolkata and Mumbai, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sea level in reference to Everest was first measured during the Great Trigonometric Survey, a Herculean effort to survey the height of the world’s tallest mountains, to measure the curvature of the Earth and mean sea level in British India. People “carried in” sea level , bringing the measurement done at the coast inland by marching miles and miles from the coast to Nepal with two bars. They measured the elevation change over a given ground distance by calculating the difference between the height of the two bars using a mounted, swiveling level, according to the Himalayan Club, a climbing and expedition club that provides scholarly information and history on the Himalayas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sea level in reference to Everest was first measured during the Great Trigonometric Survey, a Herculean effort to survey the height of the world’s tallest mountains, to measure the curvature of the Earth and mean sea level in British India. People “carried in” sea level , bringing the measurement done at the coast inland by marching miles and miles from the coast to Nepal with two bars. They measured the elevation change over a given ground distance by calculating the difference between the height of the two bars using a mounted, swiveling level, according to the Himalayan Club, a climbing and expedition club that provides scholarly information and history on the Himalayas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sea level in reference to Everest was first measured during the Great Trigonometric Survey, a Herculean effort to survey the height of the world’s tallest mountains, to measure the curvature of the Earth and mean sea level in British India. People “carried in” sea level , bringing the measurement done at the coast inland by marching miles and miles from the coast to Nepal with two bars. They measured the elevation change over a given ground distance by calculating the difference between the height of the two bars using a mounted, swiveling level, according to the Himalayan Club, a climbing and expedition club that provides scholarly information and history on the Himalayas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sea level in reference to Everest was first measured during the Great Trigonometric Survey, a Herculean effort to survey the height of the world’s tallest mountains, to measure the curvature of the Earth and mean sea level in British India. People “carried in” sea level , bringing the measurement done at the coast inland by marching miles and miles from the coast to Nepal with two bars. They measured the elevation change over a given ground distance by calculating the difference between the height of the two bars using a mounted, swiveling level, according to the Himalayan Club, a climbing and expedition club that provides scholarly information and history on the Himalayas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sea level in reference to Everest was first measured during the Great Trigonometric Survey, a Herculean effort to survey the height of the world’s tallest mountains, to measure the curvature of the Earth and mean sea level in British India. People “carried in” sea level , bringing the measurement done at the coast inland by marching miles and miles from the coast to Nepal with two bars. They measured the elevation change over a given ground distance by calculating the difference between the height of the two bars using a mounted, swiveling level, according to the Himalayan Club, a climbing and expedition club that provides scholarly information and history on the Himalayas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sea level in reference to Everest was first measured during the Great Trigonometric Survey, a Herculean effort to survey the height of the world’s tallest mountains, to measure the curvature of the Earth and mean sea level in British India. People “carried in” sea level , bringing the measurement done at the coast inland by marching miles and miles from the coast to Nepal with two bars. They measured the elevation change over a given ground distance by calculating the difference between the height of the two bars using a mounted, swiveling level, according to the Himalayan Club, a climbing and expedition club that provides scholarly information and history on the Himalayas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sea level in reference to Everest was first measured during the Great Trigonometric Survey, a Herculean effort to survey the height of the world’s tallest mountains, to measure the curvature of the Earth and mean sea level in British India. People “carried in” sea level , bringing the measurement done at the coast inland by marching miles and miles from the coast to Nepal with two bars. They measured the elevation change over a given ground distance by calculating the difference between the height of the two bars using a mounted, swiveling level, according to the Himalayan Club, a climbing and expedition club that provides scholarly information and history on the Himalayas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sea level in reference to Everest was first measured during the Great Trigonometric Survey, a Herculean effort to survey the height of the world’s tallest mountains, to measure the curvature of the Earth and mean sea level in British India. People “carried in” sea level , bringing the measurement done at the coast inland by marching miles and miles from the coast to Nepal with two bars. They measured the elevation change over a given ground distance by calculating the difference between the height of the two bars using a mounted, swiveling level, according to the Himalayan Club, a climbing and expedition club that provides scholarly information and history on the Himalayas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading at level 4 (H4)
Nowadays, geographers use a mathematical expression to estimate sea level. They imagine what would happen if there were no winds or tides, and all the water from the seas could reach interior continental areas by means of tiny, narrow channels. This creates an idealized bumpy, irregularly shaped spheroid that represents mean sea level, called a geoid, from which elevations can then be measured, according to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading at level 6 (H6)
Despite sophisticated gravimeters, complicated equations and fancy tools like global positioning systems, the elevation of Mount Everest is only precise to within a foot or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;16:9 ratio vvv&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/324868681?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=e2e43a&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;postvideo-16-9-ratio&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    I love to test me captions.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3:4 ratio ^^^&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/50397475?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=e2e43a&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;postvideo-4-3-ratio&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Yolo
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Lia Prins</name></author><category term="mountains" /><category term="measurements" /><category term="geology" /><category term="Mars" /><category term="volcanoes" /><category term="science" /><category term="supercalifragilisticexpialidocious" /><category term="superdupertrooper" /><category term="all" /><summary type="html">On maps, a mountain’s height is always shown solely as its peak’s elevation above sea level. This seems like a bit of a cop-out &amp;#58; is the mountain itself really that tall? Or is it just standing on the shoulders of a very tall plateau, so to speak? Then again, determining the base from which to measure any mountain seems like quite the slippery slope once you get down to it, so I do understand and sympathize with the sea level approach adopted by us Earthlings. But what about pinnacle-filled planets and moons that lack oceans—(how) do we measure their mountains? And even on Earth, how are the high and low tides of sea level reconciled in order to arrive at heights so specific that they often indicate individual feet, and even inches in some cases?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How does carbonless copy paper work?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/carbonless-copy-paper" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How does carbonless copy paper work?" /><published>2017-04-09T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/carbonless-copy-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/carbonless-copy-paper">&lt;p&gt;Operation
Carbonless copy paper also known as CCP, non-carbon copy paper, or NCR paper consists of sheets of paper that are coated with micro-encapsulated dye or ink or a reactive clay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The back of the first sheet is coated with micro-encapsulated dye (referred to as a Coated Back or CB sheet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The YAML can be found in _data/bar-chart.yaml, but is transformed into the JSON needed for this chart, using /data/bar-chart.json, demonstrating how YAML can be used to drive visualizations on Github.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lowermost sheet is coated on the top surface with a clay that quickly reacts with the dye to form a permanent mark (Coated Front, CF). Any intermediate sheets are coated with clay on top and dye on the bottom (Coated Front and Back, CFB).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carbonless copy paper also known as CCP, non-carbon copy paper, or NCR paper consists of sheets of paper that are coated with micro-encapsulated dye or ink or a reactive clay. The back of the first sheet is coated with micro-encapsulated dye (referred to as a Coated Back or CB sheet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello World
The lowermost sheet is coated on the top surface with a clay that quickly reacts with the dye to form a permanent mark (Coated Front, CF). Any intermediate sheets are coated with clay on top and dye on the bottom (Coated Front and Back, CFB).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the sheets are written on with pressure, as with a ball-point pen; or impact like a typewriter or dot matrix printer, the pressure causes the micro-capsules to break and release their dye. Since the capsules are so small, the resulting print is very accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carbonless copy paper was also available in a self-contained version that had both the ink and the clay on the same side of the paper. The average carbonless copy paper contains a high concentration of Bisphenol A (BPA), an endocrine disruptor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/carbonless-copy-paper/peacock-feathers.jpg&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uses
Carbonless copy paper was first produced by the NCR Corporation. Formerly, the options were to write documents more than once or use carbon paper, which was inserted between the sheet being written upon and the copy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;pink
yellow, ochre, lemon, sunny, school bus, Dixon Ticonderoga, buttercup, sunflower, daisy
white
Carbonless paper was used as business stationery requiring one or more copies of the original, such as invoices and receipts. The copies were often paper of different colors (e.g. white original for customer, yellow copy for supplier’s records, and other colors for subsequent copies). Stationery with carbonless copy paper can be supplied collated either in pads or books bound into sets, or as loose sets, or as continuous stationery for printers designed to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/carbonless-copy-paper/paper-crane.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Painting of a paper crane.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Pressure applied to carbonless-copy paper causes the clay to absorb the ink from their tiny homes.&lt;p class=&quot;figcaptionspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;I made 999 cranes but I'm just too much of a glutton for self-destruction to make one more.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dyes and chemicals
The first dye used commercially in this application was crystal violet lactone, which is widely used today. Other dyes and supporting chemicals used are PTSMH (p-toluene sulfinate of Michler’s hydrol), TMA (trimellitic anhydride), phenol-formaldehyde resins, azo dyes, DIPN (diisopropyl naphthalenes), formaldehyde isocyanates, hydrocarbon-based solvents, polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, polyoxypropylene diamine, epoxy resins, aliphatic isocyanates, Bisphenol A, diethylene triamine, and others. The dyes in carbonless copy papers may cause contact dermatitis in sensitive persons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health and environmental concerns
Until the 1970s, when the use of polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) was banned due to health and environmental concerns, PCBs were used as a transfer agent in carbonless copy paper. PCBs are readily transferred to human skin during handling of such papers, and it is difficult to achieve decontamination by ordinary washing with soap and water. In Japan, carbonless copy paper is still treated as a PCB-contaminated waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the sheets are written on with a ball-point pen, the pressure causes the micro-capsules to break and release their dye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exposure to certain types of carbonless copy paper or its components has resulted, under some conditions, in mild to moderate symptoms of skin irritation and irritation of the mucosal membranes of the eyes and upper respiratory tract. A 2000 review found no irritation or sensitization on contact with carbonless copy paper produced after 1987. In most cases, good industrial hygiene and work practices should be adequate to reduce or eliminate symptoms. These include adequate ventilation, humidity, and temperature controls; proper housekeeping; minimal hand-to-mouth and hand-to-eye contact; and periodic cleansing of hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a 1997 study, the University of Florida found that a poorly-ventilated office where large amounts of carbonless copy paper were used had significant levels of volatile organic compounds present in its air, whereas a well-ventilated office where little such paper was used did not. The study also found that there were higher rates of sick leave and illness complaints at the office using large amounts of carbonless copy paper. Another study, which was published in Environmental Health Perspectives, connected chronic occupational exposure to paper dust and carbonless copy paper with an increased risk of adult-onset asthma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2001, three employees of a medical center in San Francisco filed a lawsuit against their employer, blaming exposure to carbonless copy paper and other chemicals for their inflammatory breast cancer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lia Prins</name></author><category term="paper" /><category term="technology" /><category term="all" /><category term="officesupplies" /><summary type="html">Carbonless copy paper is a type of coated paper designed to transfer information written on the front onto sheets beneath. It was developed by chemists Lowell Schleicher and Barry Green, as an alternative to carbon paper and is sometimes misidentified as such. Instead of inserting a special sheet in between the original and the intended copy, carbonless copy paper has micro-encapsulated dye or ink on the back side of the top sheet, and a clay coating on the front side of the bottom sheet. When pressure is applied (from writing or impact printing), the dye capsules rupture and react with the clay to form a permanent mark duplicating the markings made to the top sheet. Intermediary sheets, with clay on the front and dye capsules on the back, can be used to create multiple copies; this may be referred to as multipart stationery.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do indoor trees have growth rings?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/indoor-tree-growth-rings" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do indoor trees have growth rings?" /><published>2017-04-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/indoor-tree-growth-rings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/indoor-tree-growth-rings">&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/indoor-tree-growth-rings/pine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tall tall tree&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Such a slender specimen can trace its roots back to mid-century Indo-European trading routes.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we are yet unable to predict future climate with certainty, the information locked within trees has become a standard scientific gauge, one used to date mysterious ruins, recall times of insect plagues and centuries-long drought, and chronicle distant volcanic eruptions. And, as if to fulfill Douglass’ prophecy, scientists are now using their ability to decode the information in trees to successfully forecast the seasonal conditions that lead to severe episodes of wildfire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/indoor-tree-growth-rings/annotated-tree-rings.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A man standing next to a tree cross-section that is double his height.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    The largest tree ring was born in 550 AD.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rosetta trees?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legacy of A. E. Douglass now resides in “a warren of dim rooms” tucked beneath the football stadium at the University of Arizona. There, in the Laboratory of Tree Ring Research (LTRR), nearly a million specimens of wood⏤from pen-sized cores to cross sections the diameter of small silos⏤are used to ferret out the secrets of the past, including those of climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/indoor-tree-growth-rings/european-panorama-of-austria.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Just a little caption.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as dendrochronology, the science of tree rings has matured and perhaps a thousand people worldwide are now reading the stories that reside in living trees or in ancient timbers found at archeological sites. While Douglass became famous for his studies of Pueblo ruins,&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;-1&quot; class=&quot;notenumberinline s-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-notes-id=&quot;1&quot; data-notes=&quot;&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
he knew that an understanding of the effects of changing weather on trees was critical if the technique was to be at all viable, says Martin Munro, a researcher at the LTRR.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;-2&quot; class=&quot;notenumberinline s-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-notes-id=&quot;2&quot; data-notes=&quot;&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
The dendrochronologist, says Munro, reads the distinctive patterns of wide and narrow rings which appear in pieces of wood from different trees. It is more than simply a matter of counting rings.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;-3&quot; class=&quot;notenumberinline s-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-notes-id=&quot;3&quot; data-notes=&quot;&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Patterns from different trees must be matched to pinpoint the year a tree produced a particular ring, a process known as crossdating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Year-to-year changes in the weather create the patterns, says Munro. Trees respond to temperature, rainfall and other environmental conditions by altering growth. In boom years, the tree adds extra tissue and the ring will be correspondingly thick. During lean years, growth is slowed and rings are thinner. While that sounds like a straightforward way to get at the issue of climate, Munro notes that it is not all that simple3. Trees grow better or worse in response to a combination of weather conditions, depending on their physiology and where they are growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/indoor-tree-growth-rings/log-jam.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Just a teeny weeny log jam. No big deal.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Some trees might respond to changes in overall rainfall, others to the amount of rain during the late summer, and others to the seasonal temperatures that limit the length of the growing season.” Other things, like the scars inflicted by fire and plagues of insects, also leave characteristic but indirect clues to climate since widespread forest fires and insect infestations are favored by certain conditions of weather. Human activities such as smelting and the burning of fossil fuels etch their signatures in wood as well. Dendrochronologists interested in global climate change have paid special attention to very long-lived trees like the bristlecone pines in the White Mountains of California. These trees are the oldest living organisms on Earth, providing in some cases 5,000-year-long chronologies of growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the bristlecone pines and other Methuselahs of the tree world settle into a quiet old age, they are unperturbed by these influences and can be used to document the effects of global warming, Munro says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short-lived trees, it is hard to disentangle slight changes in growth caused by gradual changes in climate. But once the bristlecone pines and other Methuselahs of the tree world settle into a quiet old age, they are unperturbed by these influences and can be used to document the effects of global warming, Munro says. Scientists speculate the gnarled and ancient trees may be the first and most sensitive biotic indicator of changes to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get Shorty
Dendrochronologists also have sought evidence of global change in shorter-lived trees in those parts of the world where climatic change would be most pronounced. For example, many people think global warming would be more of an issue nearer the poles. That idea has made trees from Alaska, Scandinavia and Siberia prime candidates for study. The advantage of using trees to study climate is that they are living records of past climate and weather. Those records are available in parts of the world where there are few weather stations and where consistent and accurate records of weather rarely go back more than 100 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/indoor-tree-growth-rings/palm-tree-cross-section.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A chopped down palm tree without any climate-caused rings.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Did you know palm trees don't form tree rings? This may be a clue to solving our mystery.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, tree ring data can be replicated by taking and comparing multiple samples to ensure that a signal is not peculiar to a single tree or stand of trees. “Dendrochronology is not simply a matter of reading single climatic variables” from a single tree, says Munro. There are lots of things there to measure, count and compare.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sheriff of Choppingham (looks like a wolf)</name></author><category term="trees" /><category term="biology" /><category term="all" /><category term="science" /><category term="botany" /><category term="plants" /><category term="forestry" /><category term="wood" /><category term="treerings" /><summary type="html">When Andrew Ellicott Douglas, director of the University of Arizona's Steward Observatory, published his fascinating chronicle of discovery in National Geographic nearly seven decades ago, it was clear to him that he had found a long-overlooked “key to prehistoric chronology.” Perhaps even more startling, was his sense that one day the concentric rings of wood laid down by trees as they grew would be a barometer for measuring future climate &amp;#58; “When a &quot;real&quot; theory of climate has been developed and we can predict drought and flood over a period of years, this Arizona story in tree rings will have played a creditable part in developing that climatic foresight which is perhaps the most valuable economic advantage yet lying beyond our reach!”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Helium Harvest</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/helium-harvest" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Helium Harvest" /><published>2016-12-10T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2016-12-10T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/helium-harvest</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/helium-harvest">&lt;p&gt;The federal government, which sets helium prices, announced in April of 2012 that helium prices would spike from $75.75 per thousand cubic feet (Mcf) this fiscal year to $84 per Mcf in fiscal year 2013. (The year prior, prices rose only 75 cents.) This price spike, along with uncertain federal policy (and a peculiar industry setup to begin with), is threatening to create a shortage. Thanks to Star Talk podcast with Neil deGrasse Tyson and Chuck Nice, I now know it’s not economically feasible to attempt to harvest helium from the sky or outer space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helium hotspot
Although helium is the second most abundant element in the universe, most of it in the Earth’s atmosphere bleeds off into space. Helium used for industrial purposes is a byproduct of natural gas production, and the Texas Panhandle is the United States’ helium capital. In the natural gas fields near Amarillo, the U.S. government maintains the country’s largest helium storehouse. The government put it there back in 1925 because natural gas produced at the gas fields between Amarillo and Hugoton, Kansas, has a very high helium concentration—up to 1.9%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although helium is the second most abundant element in the universe, most of it in the Earth’s atmosphere bleeds off into space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although other countries produce helium, the natural gas fields elsewhere around the globe are much less helium-rich than those near Amarillo. Because helium was critical to military reconnaissance and space exploration in the mid-20th Century, Congress mandated that the government encourage private helium producers nationwide to sell their helium to the government and store it near Amarillo as part of the Federal Helium Program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the U.S. alone produces 75% of the world’s helium. Nearly half of that total, or roughly 30% of the world’s helium supply, comes from the U.S. Federal Helium Reserve. That reserve is held in a huge natural underground reservoir near Amarillo called the Bush Dome. The dome is connected to a pipeline that links the stored helium with nearby helium refining facilities and the natural gas fields in Kansas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet the American reserve is in danger. Between 10 and 12 billion cubic feet of recoverable helium are expected to remain in the reservoir by the end of 2014, Walter Nelson, director of helium sourcing for Air Products and Chemicals, Inc., told the U.S. Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee in May. “At current production rates of about 2 billion cubic feet per year, the reservoir could continue to produce helium for five to six more years.” But, he said, the computer modeling that predicts the amount of helium the reservoir will be able to produce, considering its complex geology, has determined that the reservoir production rates “will decline to approximately 1 billion cubic feet per year after 2014,” he said. “As a result, the usable life of the reservoir will be extended to 2018 or perhaps even 2020.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because of politics, the reserve may not make it even that far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A government-mandated shortage?
Where Congress once mandated that the federal government keep a reserve of this crucial gas, it reversed course several decades later. In 1996, Congress moved to privatize the federal helium program, requiring all of the government’s helium supplies to be sold off by 2015. “The legislation in 1996 says we were supposed to get out of the helium business,” says Joe Peterson, the Bureau of Land Management’s assistant field manager for helium in Amarillo. “The hope was by 2015, by the time the reserve was sold down, that new sources of helium would be online and take up the demand. However, it has not happened yet.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though new private helium production plants are set to come online in the coming years—including a Wyoming plant expected to open later this year—private industry hasn’t been as interested in producing helium as Congress hoped. Until more companies begin producing helium on their own, consumers are left with spiking prices and tightening supplies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the federal system, those prices are unstable partly because they have less to do with supply and demand than they do about the need for the government, under the U.S. Bureau of Land Management, to pay off the cost of creating the Federal Helium Reserve, according to David Joyner, president of Air Liquide Helium America, who testified before the Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee in May. Helium prices were set by the BLM based on the amount of the remaining $1 billion debt the government incurred after it purchased its helium stockpile in 1960 and how much of that reserve was left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Because the original base pricing of federal helium started at below market levels, the BLM, at the recommendation of the National Academy of Sciences, is now making unpredictable increases to adjust for the base pricing up to market levels and to incorporate additional fees for costs that are specific only to the operation of the BLM reserve,” he told the committee. This irregular pricing, he said, “drives up the price of helium for all consumers, not only here in the United States, but also around the world whenever the BLM crude price is adjusted.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When helium dries up
As helium reserves tighten, the greatest impact could be on healthcare and small-scale scientific research. For example, a shortage could restrict the ability to obtain an MRI, too, if scanners become difficult to maintain with little helium to be found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Helium is absolutely essential to MRI production,” says Tom Rauch, global sourcing manager for GE Healthcare, one of the largest manufacturers of MRI systems. The most important component of an MRI system is a large magnet containing superconducting wire cooled to 4.2 Kelvin, or minus 452 F. “Helium is currently the only element on Earth that can effectively keep the magnet this cold and consequently allow for the high field strength, and stable and uniform magnetic fields that make modern MRI systems possible,” he says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the supply constraint on helium continues unabated, it could be very harmful to patient care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, he says, though companies like GE are trying to conserve as much helium as possible during the manufacturing process, MRI machines need a lot of it: up to 10,000 liters of helium, with up to 2,000 liters remaining in a sealed vacuum system around the magnet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If the supply constraint on helium continues unabated, it could be very harmful to patient care,” he says. “If there were no helium to properly service an MRI, a ‘quench,’ or sudden boil-off could occur. While there is no immediate patient safety risk, a magnet could sustain permanent damage and may need to be replaced—an expensive and time-consuming process.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other scientific fields might not require such a volume of the gas. But, according to Moses Chan, a Penn State University physics professor and member of a National Research Council committee studying the impact of selling the helium reserve, the grants that fund those researchers don’t account for volatile price swings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A way out?
Getting the government out of the helium business completely isn’t possible yet, Nelson said, because private industry’s response to the required government sell-off has been too slow and the geology of the helium reservoir near Amarillo is too complex to simply sell off the helium stored inside and then close its doors. “If the valve was simply left wide open to deplete the entire supply at once, valuable helium would be stranded in the ground and never recovered,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/helium-harvest/he-diagram.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A diagram shows the layers of Earth that house helium deposits.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Helium is actually mined from the earth, not the sky!
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Senate is considering a bill called the Helium Stewardship Act of 2012. It would extend the 2015 deadline for the sell-off of the Federal Helium Program and allow the federal government to continue supplying world markets with helium, selling it at market prices instead of government-set prices. Nelson testified on behalf of the bill, saying that if it’s not passed, the funding mechanism for the BLM’s helium operations will expire, leaving researchers and MRI manufacturers in the cold by the end of next year. But Congress has taken no action on the bill since its introduction in April.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lia Prins</name></author><category term="elements" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="all" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html">One of the most abundant elements in the universe is getting harder to come by. Helium goes into a lot more than balloons. Because the gas is inert and has extreme melting and boiling points—both near absolute zero—scientists use it in cryogenics, high-energy accelerators, arc welding, and silicon wafer manufacturing. A severe reduction in the availability of helium could force hospitals to replace costly MRI magnets or restrict patient access to them. Let's see what's going on.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Testing Forrest Gump’s chocolate box credo: do you really never know what you’re gonna get?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/testing-forrest-gump" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Testing Forrest Gump’s chocolate box credo: do you really never know what you’re gonna get?" /><published>2016-05-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-05-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/testing-forrest-gump</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/testing-forrest-gump">&lt;p&gt;The most commonly used phrase in this language is the classic assorted box of chocolates. Sure, it’s a nice gesture. Most people enjoy chocolate candies. They don’t need to be cut (although this would help us by revealing their &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/testing-forrest-gump/#-cross-section&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;--cross-section&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;-cross-section&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;cros-sections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
, chilled, prepared, and they are less likely to cause guilt, due to their diminutive size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/testing-forrest-gump/chocolate-stairs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chocolate stairs&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    All the same shape, but this chocolate's color has been altered to indicate flavors...kind of like those super fancy bars of soap. 😳.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the box of chocolates comes with baggage — the anxiety of the unknown. We’ve all been there. You mosey on into the break-room and see a surprise box of chocolates. You’re not an animal, so you’re going to indulge. But you can’t stand the thought of biting into the raspberry creme one, or worse, the monstrosity that is the cherry cordial. You so badly want the chocolate or vanilla buttercream, the nougat, or the caramel one. But the thought of biting into the chocolate with the orange creme sends you into a bout of existential vertigo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fear not, friends, I have stumbled upon a very simple rule to help you navigate through the box of chocolates: If the candy is square and tall, you are safe — it’s bound to be a non-fruit filled candy. If it’s round, it will tend to be fruit creme filled. Try it at your own risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/testing-forrest-gump/chocolate-illustration.jpg&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, some boxes of chocolates come with guides — a printed paper that shows how the treats are laid out in the box, with their shapes, and tells you what’s in them. This is great, and if you encounter a box with a guide, you can safely dive in. But it is not the common practice. The square/circle rule can help you to pick what you’re looking for in the absence of a guide.
I’m here to help, and I hope this principle has helped you. Let me know how it works for you this holiday season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;gallery&quot; id=&quot;chocolate-samples&quot;&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/testing-forrest-gump/chocolate-samples/chocolate-samples_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Alt text forrest gump 1&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          The chocolate industry seems to have no rhyme or reason for the exterior &quot;design&quot; of their goods. Meanwhile, the insides are quite compelling, and seem tastefully designed (always, the pun will be intended with me) visually as well.
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/testing-forrest-gump/chocolate-samples/chocolate-samples_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Alt text forrest gump 2&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          Candy bars look much more appetizing on the inside than the outside, so why does all the goodness have to stay hidden?
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Lia Prins</name></author><category term="chocolates" /><category term="design" /><category term="all" /><category term="lollipop" /><summary type="html">Forrest Gump was wrong. There is a way to know what you’re going to get in a box of chocolates — mostly. This time of year, at least in the US, the gift packages and treats come flying in (sometimes literally) from vendors and customers. People are saying “thank you” or “hey, how about sending some more business our way” — and they’re doing it the international language of business &amp;#58; food.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fluorescence and phosphorescence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/flourescence-and-phosphorescence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fluorescence and phosphorescence" /><published>2016-04-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-04-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/flourescence-and-phosphorescence</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/flourescence-and-phosphorescence">&lt;p&gt;General uses of fluorescence
While the marks made by fluorescent highlighters quickly draw our attention to important points in a document, fluorescence is also useful in a number of safety applications, as a scientific research tool, and in investigative medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how exactly does a fluorescent color fluoresce? It’s all about energy. A fluorescent dye molecule begins at the lowest state of energy possible – the Ground State. When light shines on it, a photon of light is absorbed by the molecule. In effect, energy is absorbed. This excites the electrons inside the molecule to higher energy states – known as the Excited State. The excited electrons soon lose some of their energy to their surroundings, which prompts them to transition back to their unexcited state – the Ground State. In order to transition back, the electrons need to emit the photon of light absorbed. This flash of light (the emission of the photon) is the fluorescence we see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/flourescence-and-phosphorescence/light-diagram.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A diagram shows the levels electrons occupy and their corresponding states.&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface&quot;&gt;
    &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
    Both florescent and phosphorescent light is caused by trapped electrons, releasing their energy as light at different rates.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluorescent paint, or black light paint, glows in ultraviolet light. This is an example of photoluminescence. Phosphorescent paints also emit light when excited by visible or ultraviolet light, but do so over extended periods. This long-lasting effect of phosphorescents also allows kids to enjoy “glow-in-the-dark” adhesive stars on the ceilings of their rooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, the Earth’s gravitational field gradually slowed the Moon’s rotation until the orbital period and the rotational speed stabilized, making one side of the Moon always face the Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;pullquotecircle&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;l-textface pullquote bold&quot;&gt;Over time, the Earth’s gravitational field gradually slowed the Moon’s rotation until the orbital period and the rotational speed stabilized, making one side of the Moon always face the Earth!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common phosphorescents include petroleum jelly, glow-in-the-dark paints, the quinine in tonic water, and some detergents. Clocks and watches have their faces or numbers and hands coated with phosphorescent paints so that we can see the time in the dark. Emergency routes, doors, and stairways are often marked with theses paints so we can find our way out of buildings when the power fails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most familiar applications is the fluorescent light bulb. When the light bulb is turned on, an electrical current passes through mercury vapor in the light bulb. The current excites the mercury atoms. As electrons in the mercury atoms drop back from their excited state to their ground state, they emit photons of ultraviolet light. The inner surface of the glass tube is coated with a fluorescent chemical, which emits light when excited by this ultraviolet light. These tubes are more efficient and longer lasting than incandescent bulbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;pullquotesquare&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;l-textface pullquote bold&quot;&gt;Over time, the Earth’s gravitational field gradually slowed the Moon’s rotation until the orbital period and the rotational speed stabilized, making one side of the Moon always face the Earth!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, the Earth’s gravitational field gradually slowed the Moon’s rotation until the orbital period and the rotational speed stabilized, making one side of the Moon always face the Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other applications of fluorescence in safety equipment include marine buoys and road signs, which also make use of fluorescent paints. Fluorescent or black light paints tend to be bright in color, with yellow, green, orange, and red being common hues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluorescence is used to enhance various kinds of investigation, from the study of genes and cell structure using fluorescence microscopy, to locating useful mineral resources such as oil and gems. Substances that fluoresce naturally make the subject easier to study; for instance, scorpions fluoresce and are much easier to see in ultraviolet light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical research makes widespread use of fluorescence to understand biological processes and in diagnosis. Fluorescent dyes may be used to mark antibodies, for example, or can reveal the flow of body fluids like blood or tears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluorescence and photoluminescence
Fluorescence and photoluminescence are further applications of useful doped semiconductors. Dopants are used to reduce the energy band gap and produce visible light in substances that would normally emit ultraviolet light. In semiconductor materials containing donor and acceptor impurities, ultraviolet or electrical energy may be absorbed to excite an electron from the valence band directly to the conduction band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electron may take a return path via the donor and acceptor energy levels. These energy differences are smaller than the natural band gap, and correspond to wavelengths in the visible light spectrum. Visible light may be emitted as fluorescence or electroluminescence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;gallery&quot; id=&quot;naturally-occurring-phosphorescence&quot;&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/flourescence-and-phosphorescence/naturally-occurring-phosphorescence/naturally-occurring-phosphorescence_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/flourescence-and-phosphorescence/naturally-occurring-phosphorescence/naturally-occurring-phosphorescence_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          So much brightness!
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluorescence occurs in “phosphor” powders, such as zinc sulfide (ZnS) containing copper (Cu) and other additives. Phosphors were once used inside television screens, activated by a stream of electrons (cathode rays). Again, tailoring the impurity levels enabled the production of fluorescence in a desired color. The colors on early television screens were created by mixing red, green, and blue light from this fluorescence. A phosphor coating is also used in high-power LED lamps. The light emitted by the diode excites the phosphor layer to fluoresce, increasing the output by up to 20%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To produce electroluminescence, photoluminescent powder is spread between two electrodes. Electrical current passing through the powder excites electrons to the conduction band. As electrons in the donor level are ‘accepted’ by holes in the acceptor level, visible light is emitted. Nightlight panels are made using this technology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sheriff of Choppingham (looks like a Wolf)</name></author><category term="light" /><category term="all" /><category term="science" /><category term="physicalscience" /><summary type="html">The production of light from heat, or incandescence, is familiar to everyone. But other processes can also yield light – without ever using heat. The term photoluminescence describes a process that produces light using light energy. Two forms of photoluminescence &amp;#58; fluorescence and phosphorescence, are defined by the length of time the emitted light continues to glow. Fluorescence refers to the immediate release of light, where light is emitted within a fraction of a second after excitation. Phosphorescence refers to the release of light that lasts longer – sec­onds or even hours after the excitation has stopped. Phosphorescence is a longer-lasting process than fluorescence because of the structure of the molecules at the quantum level. The energy transitions from excited, higher energy states to stable ground states are “forbidden” by quantum rules. In real terms, they do in fact occur, but at such low probabilities that these energy transitions last a very long time.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">License plate logic and secret codes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/license-plate-logic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="License plate logic and secret codes" /><published>2015-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2015-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/license-plate-logic</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/license-plate-logic">&lt;p&gt;In addition to my betrothed crayons, I loved my notebooks; I had one for each obsession of the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testing inline definition formatting
Today we will be testing all possible configurations of inline vocab definitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just testing out a defined word &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/license-plate-logic/#pai&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;-pai&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;pai&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;pasta (PAI)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
, right here!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just testing out a defined word &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/license-plate-logic/#pa&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;-pa&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;pa&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;PA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
 right here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just testing out a defined word &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/license-plate-logic/#pi&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;-pi&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;pi&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;PI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
 right here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just testing out a defined word &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/license-plate-logic/#p&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;-p&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;p&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;P&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
 right here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just testing out a defined word &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/license-plate-logic/#ai&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;-ai&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;ai&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;AI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
 right here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just testing out a defined word &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/license-plate-logic/#a&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;-a&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;a&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;A&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
 right here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just testing out a defined word &lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/license-plate-logic/#i&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;-i&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;i&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
 right here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;dfn&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/license-plate-logic/#nothing-optional&quot; title=&quot;Learn more&quot; id=&quot;-nothing-optional&quot; class=&quot;vocabwordinline m-textface bold yellowhover&quot; data-definition-id=&quot;nothing-optional&quot; data-vocab=&quot;&quot;&gt;Nothing optional&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dfn&gt;
 right here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serial coding
License plate numbers are usually assigned in ascending order, beginning with a starting point such as AAA-001. Thus, an observer familiar with the sequence can determine roughly when the plate was issued. In a few cases, numbers have been assigned in descending order. For example, when Virginia switched to seven characters for its standard issue in 1993, numbers beginning with AAA-1000 were already in use for extra-cost, optional-issue plates; therefore, the new standard license plates were issued in descending order from ZZZ-9999.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blogposts/license-plate-logic/mexican-plate-diagram.jpg&quot; class=&quot;contentimage singleimage clickme&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;imgfullscreentoggle imgtofullscreen yellowhover&quot; title=&quot;View larger&quot; alt=&quot;View larger&quot; src=&quot;assets/images/sitewide/to-full-screen.svg&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expiration date&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some states, the month of expiration or the county of registration is incorporated into the plate's serial. The last number on a Massachusetts license plate indicates the month the vehicle's registration expires (for example, 1234 AB would expire in April, the fourth month; 0 indicates October expirations; and X and Y were used for November and December expirations, respectively, on commercial plates and pre-1978 passenger plates), as does the first number or letter on West Virginia plates (1 to 9 for January through September, and O, N, and D for October, November, and December expirations, respectively). Maine trailer plates start with two digits and a dash. All plates expire on the last day of February, and the first two digits of the plate are the year it expires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;gallery&quot; id=&quot;eu-plates&quot;&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/license-plate-logic/eu-plates/eu-plates_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Motorcycle plate&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/license-plate-logic/eu-plates/eu-plates_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Motorcycle plate 2&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          Morocco’s motorcycle plate still uses Roman digits.
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/license-plate-logic/eu-plates/eu-plates_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Motorcycle plate 3&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          Turkey’s motocycle plate still has four of each type of digit.
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;County of issuance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although increasingly few states place the full name of the county of registration explicitly on their standard-issue plates but not as part of the plate serial, Florida, Georgia, Iowa, Kentucky, Mississippi, and Tennessee continue the practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Alabama, Montana, Nebraska, South Dakota, and Wyoming, a one- or two-digit number representing the county of issue begins a license plate number. Standard-issue Idaho license plate numbers begin with a single-letter or a number-letter code representing the county of issue. County codes have been based on historical population figures, the county names in alphabetical order, or some combination thereof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;License plate numbers are usually assigned in ascending order, beginning with a starting point such as AAA-001. Thus, an observer familiar with the sequence can determine roughly when the plate was issued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only three places in the United States use letters to designate a residence where a vehicle was registered. In Hawaii, the license plates have a unique letter designation based on the island counties that residents purchased or registered the vehicles from; a vehicle with a registration number beginning with H or Z is registered in Hawai‘i County, one beginning with K is registered in Kaua‘i County, one beginning with M or L is registered in Maui County, and one beginning with any other letter (and not containing H, K, L, M, or Z) is registered in the City and County of Honolulu. In the State of Idaho the first one or two characters are used to designate the county of residence/registration. For example, all vehicles registered in Ada county start with 1A, vehicles in Twin Falls County start with 2T and vehicles in Valley county start with V (as there is only one county that starts with the letter V). In the US territory of Guam, the license plates use the first two letters that are coded by village of issuance, for example, “TM-1234” refers to a vehicle that was registered by a person who lives the village of Tamuning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Florida allows its residents to choose either “Sunshine State” or “In God We Trust” slogans instead of their county, and in Miami-Dade County, all plates are issued with one of these slogans due to the targeting for crimes of cars registered there in the early 1990s. Florida also terminated a practice by which plates registered to rented vehicles had the letter Y or Z as their first digit, which also led to targeting of cars for theft due to the ease of replacement and the softer hit on the affected driver. Georgia, as of 2011, allows drivers to choose the slogan “In God We Trust” in place of the county name where the vehicle is registered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indiana and Ohio display two-number county codes, while Kansas plates display two-letter county codes, but none of these three is a part of the plate serial and instead are placed in the corner of the plate in a smaller font size. Texas places the county name on the windshield registration sticker, but it likewise is not part of the plate serial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;gallery&quot; id=&quot;alabama-plates&quot;&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/license-plate-logic/alabama-plates/alabama-plates_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Alabama alt 1&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          The number to the left is a county code, in this case the 1 represents Jefferson County.
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/license-plate-logic/alabama-plates/alabama-plates_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Alabama alt 2&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          In 1977 Alabama started issuing plates with the counties represented by name, via a sticker at the bottom of the plate. This left more characters available on the plate itself, and more unique plates could be generated.
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/license-plate-logic/alabama-plates/alabama-plates_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Alabama alt 3&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          The 70 prefix on this 1976 Alabama license plate represents a replacement plate for a lost or stolen one.
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/license-plate-logic/alabama-plates/alabama-plates_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Alabama alt 4&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          This plates style was used in 1976 to denote exempt commodity trucks. The &quot;C7&quot; indicates a truck approved for carrying 42,001 to 62,000 pounds, issued in Covington County.
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        

        
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/blogposts/license-plate-logic/alabama-plates/alabama-plates_5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Alabama alt 5&quot; class=&quot;contentimage&quot; id=&quot;galleryimage&quot; /&gt;
        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        

        

        
        
        &lt;figcaption class=&quot;xs-textface caption gallerycaption&quot; data-galleryfigcaption=&quot;&quot;&gt;
          &lt;hr class=&quot;toprule&quot; /&gt;
          According to the ALPCA archive, in 1969 and 70 letters were added after some county code numbers to help extend the series. &quot;A&quot; represents the second set of 100,000; &quot;B&quot; represents the third set of 100,000, etc.
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
        

        
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skipped characters and visibility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For various reasons related to visibility and readability, some states and territories exclude certain letters from use in their license plate serial formats. The most commonly skipped characters are I, O, and Q, with some states using only one or two of the three while others will skip all three of these letters. Others states, such as Colorado and Georgia have gradually adopted one or more of these letters over a course of years after previously skipping them in order to accommodate the demands of population growth and depletion of available serial combinations. The most common argument behind skipping I, O, and Q is that they can be too easily confused with 0, 1, and other characters, particularly when there isn't adequate spacing or divider between numbers and letters. For this reason, California currently only uses I, O, and Q in between two other letters, an example would be &quot;1AQA000&quot;. A unique example of character use is Texas, which used to issue serials using all 26 letters but currently skips all vowels along with the letter Q.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Amateur radio license plate issues, all states that have them available, except Pennsylvania, use a unique slashed zero character in place of the standard “0” character due to lack of spacing between letters and numbers. Iowa is a unique example in the use of this character, which began using the slashed zero beginning in 2012 on all standard passenger plates as opposed to the traditional symbol for zero to differentiate it from the letter “O” which is also used.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lia Prins</name></author><category term="design" /><category term="geography" /><category term="all" /><summary type="html">Formats for license plate numbers may be consistent within the state. For example, Delaware and Rhode Island were formerly able to use six-digit all-numeric serials due to their low respective populations. Several populous states use seven-character formats of three letters and four numbers, including 1ABC234 in California and ABC1234, ABC 1234, or ABC-1234 in Arizona, Georgia, Michigan, New York, North Carolina, Ohio, Pennsylvania, Texas, Virginia, and Washington. Other formats include Florida, which uses ABC-D12; Connecticut, which uses AB-12345; Illinois, which uses AB 12345; and Maryland, which uses 1AB2345. However, many states, such as Alaska, Arkansas, Colorado, Hawaii, Indiana, Iowa, Kansas, Kentucky, Louisiana, Minnesota, Mississippi, Nebraska, North Dakota, Oklahoma, Oregon, South Carolina, and Wisconsin, use a 3-letter, 3-number format in the format ABC-123, 123-ABC, or some variant thereof.</summary></entry></feed>